Guide to the Montana State Capitol Commission Records 1895-1917
Montana Historical Society
Montana State Capitol Commission Records
1895-1917
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 65
Montana State Capitol Commission
.5 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana State Board of Examiners served ex officio as the Montana State Capitol Commission to oversee the planning and construction of the state capitol building. Records consist of correspondence (1895-1903); minutes (1895-1902, 1909-1912); an agreement (1909) for the construction of new wings; a history and description (1917) of the building; a listing and description of the paintings in the building; and a visitors' register (July 4, 1902) for the dedication ceremony.
The Montana Board of Capitol Commissioners was established by the 1895 Legislature. The Board, consisting of the governor, secretary of state, and attorney general, was given the power to review proposals submitted by contractors for the construction of a capitol building or for modifying an existing building for use as a capitol. To be approved, the building must be in a convenient location, be available by October 1, 1896, be large enough to house all state offices, and be fire-proof, with vaults for the storage of state archives. The state would then lease the building for five years. The Board signed an initial contract with George R. Mann for the building. In 1897 the law was amended to provide for the construction of a permanent capitol building for not more than $300,000. The legislature authorized the cancellation of George R. Mann's contract and the solicitation of new bids. The board was increased to five members to consist of the governor and four citizens appointed by the governor, only one of whom could be from Helena. The 1897 legislature authorized the issuance of thirty year bonds in the amount of $350,000 for the construction of the capitol building. The cornerstone of the capitol was laid July 4, 1899 on land donated by a consortium of Helena real estate men
Records consist primarily of minutes of the Commission (1895-1912). In addition, there is general correspondence (1895-1903), an agreement (1909) for the addition of the Capitol wings, and history and description of the Capitol, a listing and description of the paintings in the Capitol, and register (1902) of visitors attending the dedication of the Capitol.
The collection is arranged by series
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Architecture--designs And Plans; Capitols--Montana; West (U.S.) in art; Architecture--Montana--Helena; Helena (Mont.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Montana; Architecture; Government and Politics
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include D. Pedretti's Sons; J.H. Kent, Architect; Richard Lockey[?] re donation of land), 1895-1903 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Legal Documents
  - Agreement with Charles S. Haire and John G. Link for building of addition onto Capitol, 1909 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- Minutes
  - Minutes of State Capitol Commission, 1895 July - 1902 July (Volume Vol. 1)
  - Minutes of State Capitol Commission, 1909 March - 1910 January (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Documents removed from March 1909 minutes for preservation reasons, 1909 March (Box-folder 1 / 3a)
  - Minutes of State Capitol Commission, 1910 February - 1912 January (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Miscellany
  - History and description of Capitol Building by M.L. Rickman, 1917 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Listing and description of paintings in the Capitol Building, undated (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Register of visitors attending the dedication of the State Capitol Building, 1902 July 4 (Volume Vol. 2)